A Guide to the W. Randolph Chitwood Papers, 1836-1984
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
W. Randolph Chitwood Papers 1837-1984
Special Collections, Kegley Library
2001.1
13 folders..
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Ruth Ann Chitwood donated the Papers, as part of the W. R. Chitwood Collection, to the Kegley Library in 2001.
Biographical Information
A native of Wytheville, Virginia, Walter Randolph Chitwood was the son of Edmund Madison Chitwood Sr. and Ethel Dale Tipton and was born 20 October 1920. He graduated from Wytheville High School. He graduated Hampden Sydney College in 1941 and the University of Virginia Medical School in 1944. During World War II he served in the United States Army Medical Corps, afterwards returning home to Wytheville to practice medicine with his father at the Chitwood Memorial Clinic. He continued his medical practice until poor health forced his premature retirement in 1965 after a massive heart attack.
Dr. Chitwood then embarked upon his second career as a local historian, working with the Wythe County Historical Society and his colleague Mary B. Kegley. He published several periodical articles on various aspects of Wythe County and Southwest Virginia history. Collecting historical documents and memorabilia also consumed his time. However, Chitwood spent most of his time in the basement of the Wythe County courthouse, combing through documents to find information for articles and books. He assisted Kegley with her research for Wythe County, Virginia: a Bicentennial History. A particular interest of his was collecting information on physicians from Wythe County as well as those who served in the Confederate Army.
W. Randolph Chitwood married Ruth Reed and had three children. He served on many local boards and organizations including the Wythe County Public Library, Rotary Club, and the Wythe County Bicentennial Committee. Chitwood died 24 January 1993 and is buried in the Tipton Family Cemetery in Hillsville, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The Papers consist of draft manuscripts, typed and handwritten, of several published and unpublished works by Dr. W. Randolph Chitwood. Included are drafts of the following publications: Death and marriage notices from the South-West Virginia Enterprise, April 17, 1870 to December 28, 1881, Tombstone inscriptions, East End Cemetery and St. Mary's Catholic Church Cemetery, Wytheville, Va., and A Diary of Lucy S. Ruggles, New England teacher in the highlands of antebellum Virginia, published in the Wythe County Historical Review. Unpublished drafts include Death register, 1874-1894, Wythe County, Va., Wythe County 1850 census, and Wythe County 1860 census. Published editions of the draft manuscripts may be found in the Kegley Library.
Included in the Lucy S. Ruggles diary manuscript is research correspondence and notes; the correspondence is arranged chronologically. It consists mainly of letters written by Chitwood to various repositories including the Emma Willard School, Troy Public Library (New York), Bennington Museum (Vermont), Knoxville Public Library (Tennessee), Historical Society of Washington County (Virginia), University of Texas Library, Duke University Library, and South Carolina Historical Society. The arrangement of the research notes remains as Chitwood originally placed.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Chitwood, W. Randolph. Death and marriage notices from the South-West Virginia Enterprises, April 17, 1870-28 December 1881. Wytheville, Va.: W. R. Chitwood, 1984.
Chitwood, W. Randolph. A Diary of Lucy S. Ruggles, New England teacher in the highlands of antebellum Virginia. Wythe County Historical Review, 1979-1981. Part 1: no. 15 (Jan. 1979) p. 21-30 Part 2: no. 16 (July 1979) p. 9-22 Part 3: no. 17 (Jan. 1980) p. 7-16 Part 4: no. 18 (July 1980) p. 12-22 Part 5: no. 19 (Jan. 1981) p. 11-20.
Chitwood. Randolph Tombstone inscriptions, East End cemetery and St. Mary's Catholic cemetery, Wytheville, Virginia. 1977, 1984.
Contents List
- Folder 1. Death and marriage notices from the South-West Virginia Enterprise, April 17, 1870 - 28 December, 1881 Manuscript. 1984. (Box-folder 1:1)
  Folder includes typed draft manuscript with corrections, negative of the cover, camera ready cover, and flyer.
- Folder 2. Death and marriage notices from the South-West Virginia Enterprise, April 17, 1870 - 28 December, 1881 Manuscript. 1984. (Box-folder 1:2)
  Folder contains camera ready typed manuscript.
- Folder 3. Death register, 1874-1894, Wythe County, Va.1981. (Box-folder 1:3)
  Folder contains photocopy of handwritten transcript of Wythe County death register from courthouse basement.
- Folder 4. A Diary of Lucy S. Ruggles, New England teacher in the highlands of antebellum Virginia.1981. (Box-folder 1:4)
  Folder contains typed manuscript with corrections.
- Folder 5. A Diary of Lucy S. Ruggles, New England teacher in the highlands of antebellum Virginia.1981. (Box-folder 1:5)
- Folder 6. A Diary of Lucy S. Ruggles, New England teacher in the highlands of antebellum Virginia. Correspondence. 1970, 1975-1979, 1982. (Box-folder 1:6)
  Arranged chronologically, folder contains correspondence between Chitwood and Mrs. Robert Bivens, Emma Willard School (Troy, New York), Woods Memorial Library (Barre, Massachusetts), Troy Public Library (Troy, New York), Rogersville Chamber of Commerce (Tennessee), Bennington Museum (Vermont), Greensboro Public Library (North Carolina), King George County (Virginia), Knoxville-Knox County Public Library (Tennessee), John P. Alderman, Rogersville Public Library (Tennessee), Lillian S. Butt, Sam Stuffle, Episcopal Diocese of Virginia, Historical Society of Washington County (Virginia), Duke University Library, University of Texas Library, South Carolina Historical Society, Alester G. Holmes, Caroline Bivens, and College of the Holy Cross.
- Folder 7. A Diary of Lucy S. Ruggles, New England teacher in the highlands of antebellum Virginia. Research Notes. 1836-1983. (Box-folder 1:7)
- Folder 8. A Diary of Lucy S. Ruggles, New England teacher in the highlands of antebellum Virginia. Research Notes. 1837-1973. (Box-folder 1:8)
- Folder 9. Tombstone inscriptions, East End cemetery, and St. Mary's Catholic cemetery, Wytheville, Virginia.1984. (Box-folder 1:9)
  Folder contains typed draft manuscript with corrections.
- Folder 10. Tombstone inscriptions, East End cemetery, and St. Mary's Catholic cemetery, Wytheville, Virginia.1984. (Box-folder 1:10)
  Folder contains handwritten draft manuscript with corrections.
- Folder 11. Wythe County 1850 Census.Undated. (Box-folder 1:11)
  Folder contains handwritten transcription of 1850 Wythe County census, households 144-805.
- Folder 12. Wythe County 1850 Census.Undated. (Box-folder 1:12)
  Folder contains handwritten transcription of 1850 Wythe County census, households 806-1631.
- Folder 13. Wythe County 1860 Census.Undated. (Box-folder 1:13)
  Folder contains handwritten transcript of 1860 census, partial listing.